<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against immoderate sorrow for the death of our friends: taken from an assured hope of our resurrection to life and glory. Delivered in a sermon preached in the parish-church of North-Wraxall in Wiltshire, the 12th. of Aprill 1660. at the funeral of Sr William Button Baronet. By Francis Bayly his houshold chaplain.</title>
            <author>[Bayly, Francis, fl. 1660].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1026_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867676</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76239)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1026[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against immoderate sorrow for the death of our friends: taken from an assured hope of our resurrection to life and glory. Delivered in a sermon preached in the parish-church of North-Wraxall in Wiltshire, the 12th. of Aprill 1660. at the funeral of Sr William Button Baronet. By Francis Bayly his houshold chaplain.</title>
                  <author>[Bayly, Francis, fl. 1660].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by W. Godbid for Richard Thrale at the Cross Keys at St. Paul's Gate entring into Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: An antidote against immoderate sorrow.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119997:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST IMMODERATE SORROW for the Death of our Friends: Taken from an aſſured hope of our Reſurrection to Life and Glory.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED In a SERMON preached in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>North-Wraxall</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> The 12<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1660. At the FUNERAL of <hi>S WILLIAM B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TTON</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>By FRANCIS BAYLY his Houſhold Chaplain.</p>
            <q>Transfertur vitae morte, non aufertur: <bibl>
                  <hi>Chryſologus.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>All the dayes of mine appointed time, will I wait till my Change come.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job. c. 14.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>St. Aug. Serm. <hi>33.</hi> de ver. Apoſt.</bibl>
               <p>Deus factus homo, mori &amp; reſurgere voluit, ut &amp; qued futurum eſſet homini, in hominis carne oſtenderetur, &amp; deo tamen, non homini crederetur.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But now Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and is become the firſt fruits of them that ſlept.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 15.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid</hi> for <hi>Richard Thrale</hi> at the <hi>Croſs Keys</hi> at St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Gate</hi> entring into <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:119997:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119997:2"/>
            <head>An Antidote AGAINST <hi>IMMODERATE SORROW.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Theſſ. c. 4. v. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For if we beleive that Jeſus dyed, and roſe again, even ſo them alſo who ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Uratio funeris Vivorum ſolatium,</hi> the funerals of the dead are then beſt performed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Auguſt. civit. dei. l. <hi>1</hi> Cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> when the living are moſt comforted; and what greater comfort at a funeral, then to treat of a Reſurrection, without the hope of which, Chriſtians of all men were the moſt miſerable; for this is it which doth recompence our wet ſeeds-time with a ſerene and joyful Harveſt. Should I therefore ſtudy to chear your drooping ſpirits, and waſh away thoſe briny tears from your blubbered Cheeks for the loſſe of our dear friend, or to comfort and fortifie your hearts againſt the ſad approaches of impartial death, which way could I better compaſſe my deſign, then by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119997:3"/>you, though we muſt dye, yet we ſhall riſe again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that this mortal muſt put on immortality, and that thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus, God will bring again with him to glory; When the Ship wherein our bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> floated upon the raging billows of the foaming Ocean, was driven by a tempeſtuous <hi>Euroclydon,</hi> inſomuch that not only the Soldiers, but Mariners deſpaired of ſafety; how comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table think you (if credited) was that ſaying of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle? there ſhall not be the loſſe of any mans life, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Ship; and ſhall it be leſſe to us, that though for a time,<note place="margin">Acts 26.22.</note> out body, the Ship of the Soul, which carries her about in the raging Sea of affliction, be at length ſwallowed up of the grave, yet our ſouls ſhall ſafely arrive at the haven of happineſs, and at the laſt day, the Sepulchre that devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Leviathan</hi> muſt diſgorge her ſelf of her prey, that ſo the happineſs both of Soul and body may be conſummate and compleat, and both together partake of that inheritance, which is laid up for thoſe that love his appearance: With what cheerfulneſſe doth the laborious husbandman under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe his Winters employment, out of an expectation of a Summers return? would the Soldier think ye undergoe the Battail with ſo much courage and reſolution, were it not to gain the Victory and wear the Crown? an Heir, though in preſent want to day, yet receives comfort from the expectation of a next dayes Inheritance; we though by nature we are the children of wrath, yet by grace and adoption we are the Sons of God, and Heirs to heaven, and death doth but convey us to the poſſeſſion: well therefore might St. <hi>Peter</hi> tearm the hope of life after death <hi>Spes viva</hi> a lively hope; for the hope of life immortal is the very life of this life mortal, and that joy and gladneſſe with which it doth affect the heart, is <hi>vitae eternae initium,</hi> the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of eternal life: That anſwer (doubtleſſe) of the Angel at the Sepulchre to thoſe early, but ſuperfluouſly pious women, who came to reimbalme the body of our Saviour, <hi>reſurrexit non eſt hîc,</hi> he is riſen, he is not here,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119997:3"/>was received by them, not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but joy, and may ſtill ſound much of comfort to us, his being the very pledge and aſſurance of ours, who by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is termed <hi>primitiae dormientium,</hi> the firſt-fruits of them that ſleep;<note place="margin">Sen. Nat. Queſt. lib. 6. cap. 1.</note> the Stoick therefore erred when he ſaid, <hi>non majus mortalitatis ſolatium quam ipſamertalitas,</hi> that there is no greater comfort againſt mortality, than morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity it ſelf, for the conſideration of our immortality is a greater; it is indeed a ſtrong encouragement againſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, to think that we muſt dye yet it is a far greater, that we ſhall live again; that may cauſe us to neglect the ſtroke of death, but this to embrace it: for the beſt way to make death ſeem eaſie, is to look through death at glory, not to think ſo much that we ſhall dye, as to believe that we ſhall riſe again; the former may take away the fear of death, this mitigates our ſorrow: I would not have you ignorant brethren, concerning thoſe that are aſleep, that ye ſorrow not as others that have no hope, for if we beleeve that Ieſus dyed and roſe again, even ſo them alſo that ſleep in Ieſus will God bring with him.</p>
            <p>The ſum of my Text is a reaſon preſſing Moderation of Sorrow, taken from the certainty of Reſurrection to life: of it he layeth two grounds; Firſt, The Reſurrection of Chriſt, If you beleeve that Chriſt dyed, &amp;c. Secondly, The power of God, will God bring with him, and withal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits out the perſons to whom this bleſſing belongs, thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus. Having now ſhewed you the ſum of my Text, and drift of the Apoſtle, give me leave to explain the meaning of ſome of the words, as they lye in order, and then I ſhall lay down a propoſition or two, to enlarge my ſelfe upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si enim,</hi> if ye beleeve, and your mindes are not infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but <hi>Lyra</hi> would have <hi>ſi,</hi> to be taken here for <hi>quia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, becauſe ye beleeve; for ſaith he, it belongs unto the Articles of Faith, to beleeve that Chriſt dyed and roſe againe, even ſo thoſe that ſleep or depart out of this world, for ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Original, to ſleep, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119997:4"/>likewiſe to dye, to depart out of this world; and it is a word which is proper to expreſſe the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, whoſe death is but a repoſe of their Bodies in their Graves, and a reſt of their Souls in Gods hands.</p>
            <p>But why doth the Apoſtle expreſſe the death of Chriſt and the faithfull, by two ſeveral names? he ſayes of Chriſt who roſe and ſhall never dye, <hi>mortuum fuiſſe,</hi> that he dyed, if ye believe that Jeſus dyed? but the faithful he only calls <hi>dormientes,</hi> ſleeping: <hi>Haino</hi> gives this reaſon, <hi>Chriſtum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellat mortuum,</hi> ſaith he, he calls Chriſt dead, becauſe whilſt we hear and know that he was dead and roſe again, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may hope that we ſhall riſe againe by vertue of his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: but he calls the Elect <hi>dormientes,</hi> ſleeping, becauſe no man can ſo eaſily ſtir up his friend from ſleep, as they ſhall be raiſed from the ſleep of death.</p>
            <p>In Jeſus, ſome would have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Jeſus, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for Jeſus, becauſe when men dye for Jeſus, by occaſion of him, or for Chriſtianity ſake, God will bring them with Chriſt to a glorious Reſurrection. But others take the prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſignify the ſame with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Jeſus, that is, in the faith of Jeſus; <hi>ſub ſpe fidei hujus,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adducet cum eo,</hi> ſhall bring with him into Heaven, to enjoy that bleſſed immortality; not that the Reſurrection ſhall be partial, that the wicked ſhall not riſe, for all ſhall riſe, but all ſhall not be brought with him; for <hi>[adduci] ſignificat raptum &amp; inductionem undique in nubibus cum honore ad judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Oecumenius</hi> upon this place: for true beleevers ſhall be ſnatcht up in the Clouds to meet Chriſt with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but unbeleevers ſhall exſpect him coming down, as unworthy to meet him: for all which I ſhall obſerve theſe three things;</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Reſurrection of Chriſt is not onely the pledge and aſſurance, but the effective principle, and the procuring cauſe of our Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe, and onely thoſe, who by a true and living Faith have an intereſt in Chriſt, ſhall God bring with him to glory.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119997:4"/>
            <p> Thirdly, The death of the faithful is but a ſleep, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of their Bodies in their Graves, and a reſt of their Souls in the hand of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt of all and chiefly inſiſt on the firſt of theſe, treating of my ſecond in the cloſe of my firſt, and refer the laſt to a particular Application, and firſt of the firſt of theſe.</p>
            <p>The Reſurrection of Chriſt is not onely the pledge and aſſurance, but the effective principle, and the procuring cauſe of our Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>If ye beleeve that Chriſt dyed and roſe again, even ſo thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, here ſeems to be a rub at the entrance, and that on which all is to be built is queſtionable, for all depends upon a <hi>for,</hi> and an <hi>if;</hi> for if ye beleeve, the Family of Love beleeve it not, accounting the Hiſtories of Chriſts death and Reſurrection a meer allegory. <hi>Cerinthus</hi> the Heretick, acknowledged that Chriſt ſhould riſe, but not that he was riſen; ſo thought, and ſo think the Jewes at this day, grounding their belief upon the falſe relation of thoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned Soldiers, his Diſciples came by night and ſtole him away. <hi>O infelix aſtutia,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> O unhappy craft! <hi>O inſana ſtultitia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Rhemigius,</hi> fond dream of ſleeping Watchmen; O ſleepy and ſottiſh ſpirits that can beleeve ſuch drowſie witneſſes, and give no credit to them that were waking: <hi>Si milites dormicbant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> if the Soldiers ſlept, how could they perceive the theft? if not perceive it, how could they witneſſe it? how came the Grave cloaths to be laid in ſuch order? if they had taken away the body, <hi>linteamina non reliquiſſent,</hi> they would not have left the Linnen cloaths; if ſtoln, <hi>ſudarium involvere non curaſſent,</hi> they would not have taken ſuch a care to have laid them in order: and therefore the ſame Father con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>non enim adeo ſtultus fuiſſet fur, ut in re ſuperflua tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm laboraſſet,</hi> if the world had a thief ſo honeſt, yet not ſo fooliſh to have taken ſuch care in a matter ſo ſuperfluous; yet if both, <hi>quam oportunitatem habuiſſet?</hi> what time could
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119997:5"/>he have to ſtrip off thoſe cleaving Cere-cloths; ſo many Soldiers, ſo many Watchmen being preſent; and therefore not taken away, nor yet ſtoln, but is riſen; not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is raiſed, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is riſen, and as it is in my Text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> who roſe again; and this ſhews us the difference between his and the Reſurrections of others; others, before were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but he roſe againe; we need the help and power of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, but Chriſt by his own power; for ſaith he, <hi>Have not I power to lay down my life, and to take it up again?</hi> they roſe, <hi>iterum morituri,</hi> to dye again, and therefore ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas,</hi> that was but an imperfect Reſurrection; but Chriſt roſe to dye no more, <hi>Death hath no more dominion over him,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>it was impoſſible,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>that he ſhould be holden of it, or that his holy one ſhould ſee corruption:</hi> It is for a ſinner to ſay to Corruption, thou art my Father, and to the Worm thou art my Mother, but for our Saviour he took no Corruption with his Fleſh, the Fleſh therefore that he took, felt no Corruption; he had not lived among us, had it not been to dye for us; he had not dyed, but to riſe againe; a neceſſity there was for both, ought not Chriſt firſt to Suffer, and then to enter into his glory? a Grave could not engroſſe him, whom a Throne did expect; the jaws and belly of Hell could not alter, much leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume his ſubſtance, for this mortal muſt put on immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; not that the Humane nature was changed into the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, but the ſubſtance being the ſame, the qualities were altered; <hi>reſurrectio domini non finis fuit carnis, ſed commutatio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo,</hi> the reſurrection of the Lord was not the annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, but the change of the Fleſh: The Body was ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with refined qualities, but not diveſted of its former nature; that body which before could be wounded, is now incorruptible; that Body which before could be ſlain, is now immortal, therefore ſaith <hi>Chryſologus, gloria reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis, ſepelivit morientis injuriam,</hi> the glory of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, hath buried the diſgrace of the Grave. To <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> he ſaid, <hi>noli me tangere,</hi> touch me not; to ſignifie, he had cloathed his body with immortality: to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119997:5"/>
               <hi>videte &amp; palpate,</hi> ſee me and handle me; to give ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity he had not changed the ſubſtance but the quality; in the one ſaith <hi>Aquinas,</hi> he ſhewed <hi>gloriam reſurgen is,</hi> the rare endowments he had adorn'd it with upon his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing;<note place="margin">Aq. <hi>3. p.</hi> q. <hi>55.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi> in corp.</note> in the other he declared <hi>veritatem reſurrectionis,</hi> the evident truth of his reſurrection.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that Chriſt dyed, and roſe again, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive it; <hi>Quid nobis?</hi> What benefit is all this to us? Yes, very much, becauſe we by Faith have an intereſt in both for ſaith <hi>Calvin, Non ſibi Chriſtus, ſed nobis mortuus eſt, &amp; reſurrexit;</hi> Chriſt dyed and roſe again, not for himſelf, but us; for all the hope of ours depends upon that of his, ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. We are begotten again to a lively hope, by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead; and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tells us, there goes an influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from this reſurrection, which ſhall have an operation like that of the dew of the Spring; which when he will let fall, the earth ſhall yield her dead: on the Croſſe we may ſee him ſuffering for ſin; in his Reſurrection trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing over Death; although by his death he merited, and by his ſuffering the curſe was taken away, yet by his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, the hope of life is begotten again in us; <hi>Calvin</hi> gives this reaſon, <hi>Quia ut ille reſurgendo, &amp;c.</hi> becauſe as he by riſing became deaths Conquerour; ſo the victory of our Faith doth conſiſt in the reſurrection; agreeable to that of the Apoſtle, who dyed for our ſins, but roſe again for our juſtification. 'Tis true, the death of Chriſt is the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament, but his reſurrection is the complement of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and therefore <hi>Aquinas,</hi> amongſt other reaſons why he gives that it was neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould riſe again, makes this the laſt, but not the leaſt; <hi>ad complementum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis noſtrae,</hi> for the perfecting of our Salvation; for ſaith he, Chriſt by riſing himſelf, bequeathed unto us an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting one, he is therefore tearmed the reſurrection and the life, becauſe to us he is the Author of both. Hence St. <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 3.4. <hi>When Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, then ye alſo ſhall appear with him in glory;</hi> and as it is further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119997:6"/>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. <hi>He being made perfect, became the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of eternal ſalvation, to all them that obey him,</hi> for as in <hi>Adam</hi> all dyed, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Col.</hi> 3.18. he is called head of the Church, and firſt-born from the dead; not only becauſe he raiſed himſelf from death to immortal glory, but becauſe he is <hi>principium effectivum &amp;c.</hi> the effective principle, and cauſe of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all his Members, not only the meritorious cauſe, who by his paſſion and victory over death, merited a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reſurrection for us; as it is <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Not only the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary cauſe, for the glorious reſurrection of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> doth ſhew unto us an example of our future Reſurrection unto glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is it is <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Who ſhall change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body;</hi> but the efficient cauſe, hence by the Apoſtle he is called <hi>primitiae dormientium,</hi> the firſt fruits of them that ſlept, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20. <hi>But now is Chriſt riſen from the dead, and become the firſt fruits of them that ſlept.</hi> now he is called the firſt fruits of them that ſleep, becauſe as under the Law, the offering of the firſt fruits was the cauſe of bleſſing and conſecrating all the reſt of the fruits; <hi>primitiae enim frugum non conſecrabantur Deo ut ſolae eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſanctae, ſed ut reliquus anni proventus ſanctificaretur. Zanchie;</hi> the firſt fruits were not conſecrated unto God, that they alone might be holy, but that all the encreaſe of the year might be bleſſed, for thus were they made ſacred; one ſheaf is taken out from the reſt, which ſheaf was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firſt fruits, that in the name of the reſt in lift up aloſt and ſhaken to and fro before the Lord; that done, not only the Sheaf ſo lifted up was holy, but all the Sheaves in the Field were holy no leſſe than it; and the rule is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. If the firſt fruits be holy, all the lump is ſo too &amp; thus fareth it in the reſurrection, <hi>We are all dead</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>dead ſheaves,</hi> all, one, and that is Chriſt, was in the manner of a ſheafe taken out of the number of the dead, and in the name of the reſt, lift up from the grave, by virtue whereof, the firſt fruits being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to life, all the reſt of the dead are entitled to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119997:6"/>the ſame hope in that he was not lift up for himſelf alone; for Chriſt roſe not as a private perſon to himſelf alone, but as a publick example repreſenting and effecting it to us all: the ſame nature and property ſhall be derived from the roots to the branches, from the head to the Members; the riſing were untoward and prepoſterous, ſhould not the head riſe firſt; it were imperfect and fruitleſſe, ſhould not the Members follow after; <hi>decet quemadmodum praeceſſit caput,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> it is but natural proportion that as the head is gon before, the Members ſhould follow after, which are quickned by the ſame ſpirit, Firſt to the life of grace, then of glory; But if the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead dwell in your mortal bodies, he that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead, ſhall alſo quicken your mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal bodies; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. Whereas <hi>Oecumenius</hi> obſerves, he ſays not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween raiſing the juſt and the unjuſt; all ſhall have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their riſing again, but all ſhall not be quickned; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is of a larger extent then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is not to life alone, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to life and glory; and they are thoſe that ſleep in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, that <hi>adducet cum eo,</hi> God will bring with him, ſuch who have an intereſt in him by faith; which is the limitation of the perſons, to whom this bleſſing belongs, my next part, which I promiſed to handle, and now offers it ſelf to our Conſideration, which I reduced to this propoſition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Only thoſe who have an intereſt in Chriſt by faith, will God bring with Chriſt to glory.</p>
            <p>The wicked ſhall awake out of the duſt, and riſe again, but to endleſſe torments; it were well with theſe wretches if the Sea and Grave might ſtill retain them; better ſtill to ſay to the wormes you are my brethren and Siſters, and to corruption, thou art my mother, then having broke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance with them, to be in a far worſe family of the damned Spirits, when God ſhall diſmiſſe them with a goe ye curſed into Hell fire, prepared for the divel and his Angels; it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119997:7"/>remarkably ſet down, <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.52. That when Chriſt roſe many dead bodies of the Sts. aroſe, not one wicked man, to premoniſh us, that none ſhall riſe with him to glory, but ſuch who are incorporated into him by faith. Therefore ſaith he, whoſoever beleiveth in me, ſhall never dye, <hi>Joh.</hi> 26. That is the ſecond death; for he that hath part in the firſt reſurrection, over him the ſecond death hath no powen; it was to the faithful Servant that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>enter into the joy of the Lord,</hi> but caſt the unprofitable Servant into utter darkneſs, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. It was the Intereſt of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> had in Chriſt by faith, that enabled him to his <hi>cupio diſſolvi,</hi> I deſire to be diſſolved; and therefore was he aſſured of the Crown, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had kept the faith; <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith, henceforth, there is layed up a crown of glory for me;</hi> nothing can unty this knot, or break this union which a true faith makes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and a Chriſtian, <hi>nor life, nor death, nor powers, nor principalities,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; this enabled <hi>Moſes</hi> to contemn the pleaſures of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, becauſe he knew that in heaven he had a better and a more enduring ſubſtance. True, St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that he is the Saviour of all, but eſpecially of them that beleive for he is the Saviour of all, in that he offered up a full price for an univerſal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, but the wicked have loſt their intereſt, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of unbeleif; all ſhall riſe to judgement, the wicked to the judgement of condemnation, but the faithful to the judgement of approbation, or abſolution; which in Scripture is tearmed the judgement of life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28. for the hour ſhall come, in the which all that are in the graves, ſhall hear his voyce and come forth, the good to the reſurrection of life, and the evil to the reſurrection of condemnation; he knows how to diſtinguiſh between the rares and the wheat, between the Sheep and the Goats, as he hath a burn for the one, ſo he will burn up the other with inextinguiſhable fire; as hehath a <hi>venite</hi> for thoſe on his right hand, ſo he hath an <hi>ite maledicti, goe ye curſed</hi> for thoſe on his left hand, for he is judge of all, and ſhall raiſe all;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119997:7"/>he is head of his own Body, and ſhall quicken them; as Judge he ſhall draw all to his Tribunal ſeat, and in flaming fire ſhall render vengeance to them that have not known God; as it is 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. as head he knows his own Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and the Clouds ſhall catch them up, and they ſhall for ever remain with the Lord, for the very Spirit of our Regeneration, is the very earneſt of our Reſurrection to Glory, giving unto us a beginning of Spiritual life, and a right unto the Reſurrection of life eternal. Therefore ſaith <hi>Tertullian, per regenerationem corpora noſtra inaugurari huic reſurrections,</hi> by Regeneration our Bodies are conſecrated to this Reſurrection, and Death conveies us to the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that place which is prepared for thoſe that beleeve on him; therefore ſaith our Saviour, <hi>I go to prepare a place for you, that where I am, there you may be alſo;</hi> which in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is called an Inheritance, to ſhew the right and title we have unto it, not by Purchaſe, but of Grace; not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our merits, but the abundance of his mercy; a Kingdome, yea <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Kingdome of Heaven, to which the faithfull only have a right and title, and that by deed of gift. <hi>Fear not little flocks</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>for it is your Fathers good pleaſure, to give you the Kingdome;</hi> which the Apoſtle calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which cannot be ſhaken; ſuch whoſe joyes Eyes hath not ſeen, nor Ears heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of Man. Indeed we read Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſumptuouſly ſet forth unto us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.18. the gates and foundation thereof of Pearl and Precious Stones, not that there is any ſuch thing in Heaven, or that Heaven is any ſuch thing; but God is pleaſed to condeſcend ſo far to our weakneſſe, yea to ſenſe it ſelfe, as to pencil and limn it forth unto us, by ſuch things as ſeem moſt precious unto us; for God need not be beholding to Stones, though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, to make Heaven glorious, for God himſelfe ſills Heaven with glory, and makes it infinitely glorious; God in glory, is the glory of Heaven; to conclude, it is the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of God the Father, it is the fruition of Chriſt, that Pearl of price; it is the fruition of the holy Ghoſt, the Spirit of Comfort, it is the perfection and fulneſſe of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119997:8"/>Grace; it is an eternal Sabbath, a Reſt, a Reſt in the Lord, in whom there is all Reſt; it is a Reſt after all motions; all pantings after him here, are but Reſts in him there. But I ſhall not ſpin out the ſmall ſcantling of my time, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe thin and aery diſcourſes with the Schoolmen, by deſcribing the rare qualities that our Bodies ſhall then be adorned with; let that of the Apoſtle ſuffice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43. <hi>It is ſown in Corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption; it is ſown in diſhonor, it is raiſed in glory, it is ſown in weakneſſe, it is raiſed in power.</hi> Nor with others, poſitively and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, by defining the Time and Place of our Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ſince my Text mentions neither, onely it ſayes it will be, but when, God onely knows; for <hi>non vobis datum,</hi> ſaith our Saviour Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>to you it is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to know the times and the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put into his own hands; Acts</hi> 1.7. The Angels are ignorant of it, yea the Son of God knows it not as Man (ſay ſome) or, <hi>ut nobis aperiat,</hi> that he may declare it unto us (ſay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;) <hi>novit ſibi, neſcit mihi</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> he knows it for himſelfe, but not for me, and by it checks our curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſities, that we might not endevour to fathome that, which the Angels are content to be ignorant of. The omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent wiſdome of God keeps us ignorant of the time, that we might not alwaies be ſleeping in the bed of ſecurity, but by an holy preparation to make our ſelves worthy of Chriſts invitation, whenſoever he ſhall be pleaſed to call us; for we are apt to defer things to the laſt period of time, and like thoſe fooliſh Virgins, whoſe ſloth and ſecurity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred their entrance: <hi>ideo neſcis, ut ſemper ſis paratus,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> thou art therefore ignorant, that thou maiſt alwaies be prepared? and this was our Saviours meaning in the 13 of <hi>Marke, Take heed, watch and pray, for ye know not when the time is; that ſo whenſoever it ſhall be, we may be found in him by Faith,</hi> and then we may be ſure that God will bring us with him to glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> And as the uncertainty checks our curioſity, ſo the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of it ſerves to confute the error of the <hi>Sadduces,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119997:8"/>who held that there was no Reſurrection, nor Angels, nor Spirits, <hi>Act.</hi> 23. ſome ſuch there were in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time, how ſay ſome among you, that there is no Reſurrection? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. and I fear me too many in this our age, and ſo take away all hope of happineſſe, all encouragement unto goodneſſe. <hi>Qui enim arat, arat ut metat, qui pngnat, puguat, ut vincat, Chryſoſt,</hi> in every action the vertue of working is from a thing to come; he that ploughs, ploughs to reap, he that fights, to overcome; take away the hope of the Reſurrection, and farewell all care of godlineſſe; diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe men of this hope, then farewell Faith and Honeſty, and welcome that <hi>Epicurean</hi> Song, <hi>Let us eat and drinke, what though to morrow we dye. Calvin</hi> therefore tells us, that whoſoever denyes the Reſurrection, <hi>Eccleſiae jugulum recte petit,</hi> cuts the very throat of Religion. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> therefore tells us the many inconveniences that follow this abſurdity once granted; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. if the dead riſe not, Chriſt is not riſen, then our Preaching and your Faith is in vain, then thoſe that are aſleep in Chriſt are pariſhed, Chriſtians then of all men are moſt miſerable: why then that cuſtome of being baptized for the dead? to what end are theſe Funeral ſolemnities, if the dead riſe not at all? for ſo <hi>Beza,</hi> taking the word in the middle voice, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands this place, <hi>eur ablutione utuntur?</hi> why do you waſh the dead? do men give reſpect where there is no hope? if the Corps ſhall for ever periſh, to what end do you waſh them? either down with theſe Funeral ſolemnities, or elſe confeſſe a Reſurrrection. Nay, ſaith he, why doe we every day ſtand in jeopardy? why have I endured ſo many affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, if the dead riſe not? <hi>Sola spe pius in hac vita differt ab impio; qui futuram ſpem tollit, tollit pii, impii differentiam;</hi> in this life the godly and the wicked only differ in hope, he that takes away this hope, takes away the difference, <hi>pares crunt,</hi> then they that doe, and they that ſuffer injury are alike, then had <hi>Jacob</hi> been more fooliſh then <hi>Eſau-Noah</hi> more brutiſh then the old world, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſottiſh to leave the Court, and the Diſciples ſenſeleſſe to leave all to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119997:9"/>follow a Crucified Chriſt: But Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to make all ſure, and to ſtop the mouth of Cavil it ſelf, tells us <hi>that this mortal muſt put on immortality,</hi> upon which ſaith <hi>Teſtullian,</hi> he could not have ſpoken more plain, <hi>niſi cutem ſuam in manibus teneret,</hi> unleſſe he had taken his fleſh, and held it in his hand. And Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> writing upon the Apoſtles Creed, tells us, that it was a cuſtome in the Eaſtern Church to ſing, <hi>credo reſurrectionem hujus carnis,</hi> I beleeve the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of this fleſh; for truly, if the ſame body ariſe not, it ſhould not be called a Reſurrection, but a transformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>uiſi anima idem corpus numero reſumeret,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas;</hi> for Reſurrection of <hi>reſurgere,</hi> is <hi>denuo ſurgere, quia ſurget, quod cadet;</hi> for why ſhould not the fleſh which hath been co-worker, and joynt-martyr with the Soul, participate a proportionable guerdon with the Soul? or how can it ſtand with the juſtice of God, that one body ſhall victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fight his battails, and another which never appeared in the quarrell be honoured with the crown? for the Body and the Soul have here together been common actors either of vice or vertue, and therefore it is but juſtice and reaſon, that they ſhould communicate together the reward of their good deeds, or the puniſhment of their evil.</p>
            <p>But yet there is no truth ſo poſitive, but hath found con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, this the Atheiſt nor the Heretick can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to beleeve: let <hi>Paul</hi> preach it at <hi>Athens,</hi> they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him a babbler, for they had learnt it from their old Maſter <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that <hi>a privatione ad habitum non datur regreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that from a privation to an habit, from death to life, there can be no return. Heathen Doctors could not be perſwaded, that a thing once periſhed and gone, could in the ſame nature be reſtored again unto it ſelfe: thoſe that dreamed of a transformation of Body, and a tranſmigrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Souls, could never thinke of the Reſurrection both of Soul and Body; when we ſee that Flowers fade and live again, Seeds are not quickned unleſſe they dye, <hi>dies in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctem moritur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> each night is the laſt dayes Funeral, and then what is the morning but a Reſurrection?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119997:9"/>
               <hi>Sol quotidie naſcetur, quotia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e moritur. Chryſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Serm.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>13. the Sun is every day born, and every day dies, and daily riſeth again; the times whilſt they paſſe away periſh, when they return they revive. This <hi>Seneca</hi> the Philoſopher found out, <hi>mors intromittit vitam, non eripit, venit iterum qui nos in lucem reponet, die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> death is an intermiſſion, not a loſſe of life, there ſhall come a day of reſtauration, and theſe eyes ſhall enjoy their former light. <hi>Tertullian</hi> therefore ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to demonſtrate it from the <hi>Phaenix</hi> ſpringing up new-lived out of her own aſhes; from Flies lying dead all the Winter, and reviving with the heat of the Sun in the Summer, and ſo concludes, <hi>omnia pereundo ſervantur, omnia interitu reformantur,</hi> all things are preſerved by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, and perfected by dying: this Saint <hi>Paul</hi> thought ſo apparent, that he accounts him little leſſe then a Fool that perceives it not: <hi>Thou fool, that which thou ſoweſt is not quickned unleſſe it dye,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Why ſhould we think that God to whom nothing is impoſſible, cannot as well renew as create us? for who ſees not <hi>minus eſt reparare quod erat, quam feciſſe quod non erat,</hi> it is a work of much leſſe power to reſtore that which ſometimes was, then to create that which never had been; he that once made it of nothing, can eaſily raiſe it to it ſelf again: therefore ſaith <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Quid enim eſt, dic quaeſo facilius, an ex nihilo ad hoc, ut ſint deducere, aut diſſoluta excitare, &amp; reſtituere?</hi> I prethee tell me which is eaſieſt, either from nothing to bring them to this that they be, or being reſolved to reſtore them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? God can fetch our Members whereſoever they are, that could make them when as yet they were not: what then though thy body be overwhelmed of the Sea, and the Fiſhes devour it, entombed in the Earth, and the Worms conſume it? ſince they muſt one day juſtly reſtore what they have robb'd thee of? inſomuch that a true Chriſtian, even then, when he is expiring, may ſay with <hi>Job, I know my Redeemer liveth, and though after my Skin, Wormes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume my Body, yet in my Fleſh I ſhall ſee God:</hi> Thus <hi>Martha</hi> beleeved her brother ſhould riſe again. <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119997:10"/>
               <hi>Foelix,</hi> that he had hope of the reſurrection; and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to mourn as men without hope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the dead ſhould riſe again; yea Chriſt dyed and roſe again, and therefore likewiſe ſhall we riſe again.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſince we beleive that Chriſt is riſen, and that we ſhall one day riſe with him to glory, this ſhould teach us to ſet our affections on thoſe things that are above, that where our treaſure is, there our hearts may be alſo, and not to dore on theſe things below, which <hi>moth can corrupt, and Theives break thorew and ſteal;</hi> for ſaith the wiſe man, riches are no: for ever, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Wilt thou ſet thine eyes upon that which is not, for riches certainly make themſelves wings, and fly away as an Eagle towards Heaven. Habent</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>) <hi>ſi non finem tuum, finem ſuum, ſi non finem ſuum, finem ſuum;</hi> they have either thy end, or their own end, if not their own end, thy end; that is, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will be taken from thee, or thou muſt one day be taken from them; and as <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> hath it, <hi>nec plenitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem conferre poſſunt continenti, &amp;c.</hi> They can neither ſatisfie thoſe that have them, nor defend thoſe that truſt in them, nor being fruit to thoſe that labour for them; what there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall <hi>it profit a man to gain the whole world, and looſe his own ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou voluptuous wretch, and prodigal Spend-thrift, who doſt ſpend all thy time in hunting after the vanities of this world, whoſe God is thy belly, and glory thy ſhame, what felicity, what contentment canſt thou find in it? perhaps ſon: a time thou mayeſt pleaſe thy pallace with ſome delightful vaſt, delight thine eye with ſome exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Beauty; and hug thy ſelf with that <hi>Eplcure an Lull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bie; ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, bibe, lude,</hi> ſoul ear, drink, and take thy reſt, thou haſt much good laye drup for thee for many years, but what follows? thou ſool, this night ſhall thy ſoul be taken from thee; Thou covetous wretch and griping miſer, thou that are alwayes gaping after the much of this world, and knowes no other God but thy wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, who do's not uſe but ſerve the world, what foelicity canſt thou find in that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119997:10"/>wherein there is no fulneſſe; why doſt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after that with ſo much eagerneſſe, which is to be preſerved with ſo much care and trouble? why doſt thou become thus cruel to thy ſelf, that thou mayeſt be beneficial to thou knoweſt not whom? and heapeſt up riches, and knoweſt not who ſhall enjoy them? therefore our Saviour Chriſt to take away this carking and caring out of the minds of Chriſtians, having firſt ſent them to School to the fowls of the Air, and the Lillies of the field, who could read unto them a lecture of Gods providence; makes this inference, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take no thought, what ye eat, or what ye ſhall drink, or wherewith ye ſhall be cloathed; but ſeek yee firſt the Kingdome of heaven, and the righteouſneſſe thereof; <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jora quaeritis ad majora nati;</hi> ye are born for greater things, and therfore ſeek them upon which, ſaith <hi>Chryſologus, miſerumcui cum detur regnum ſuſpirat panem;</hi> miſerable is that man on whom a Kingdom is beſtowed, who is ſtill carking and caring for bread: that ſaying of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great when but a Prince, was a notable one, and may ſerve for our inſtruction, who when he was invited by ſome to run in a race with certain <hi>Plebejans,</hi> replyed, <hi>regis filio non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire, ut in ſtadio curreret niſi cum regibus;</hi> it became not the Son of a King to run with any but ſuch who were like himſelf, Princes: Is it for one who is running a race for ſome rich prize, to catch at every fly, or to ſtoop to take up every pebble? or for an heir apparent to the Crown, to play with toyes, or to delight with rattles? no, the child of God moves in a higher Sphear, and fixeth his contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations on better objects; they account heaven their home, this life a pilgrimage, and themſelves but ſtrangers, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith our Saviour Chriſt to his Diſciples, ye are not of this world, the wicked are of this world, as well in mind as body; the children of God, although they live in this world, yet they are not of this world; for ſaith St. <hi>Auguſt. Qui non diligunt mundum, non habitant in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d non diligunt;</hi> they that do not love the world, may not properly be ſaid to dwell in that which they do not affect; <hi>for our converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119997:11"/>is in heaven,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> whence we look for the coming of our Lord Jeſus: <hi>who ſhall change our vile bodyes, that it may be made like unto his glorious body. Phillippians</hi> 3.20.21.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>3</label> Since the death of the faithful is but a ſleep, a repoſe of their bodies in the grave, and a reſt of their ſouls in the hands of God, why ſhould we thus immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately grieve and ſorrow for the death of our friends? for their eternal Good? for their Welfare and Happineſs; <hi>Lord, if he ſleep he ſhall do well,</hi> (ſaid the Diſciple of Chriſt, concerning <hi>Lazarus</hi>) upon which ſaith St. <hi>Aug. Solet enim ſomnus aegrotantium, ſalutis indicium,</hi> The ſick mans ſleep is a fore-runner of his health; and Death is no more to Gods Children, for it not only mitigates, but wholly takes away our griefs; <hi>Ut remedium videatur non paena;</hi> St. <hi>Amb. de Cain. et Abel lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. that it might ſeeme a remedy, and not a puniſhment. <hi>Chryſologus</hi> tells us that death is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called a ſleep, becauſe no one can ſo eaſily raiſe his friend from ſleep, as God can us from the grave; for ſaith the Text, it is in a moment, in the twinckling of an eye: But <hi>Aquinas</hi> on my Text, tels us that death is called a ſleep becauſe it reſembles it in theſe two things, firſt, becauſe he that layes down to ſleep, doth it <hi>ſpe reſurgendi,</hi> out of an hope to riſe again, and Death is but aſleep ſomewhat long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then ordinary; <hi>Man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, if he dye ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened again, until the heavens be no more, Job.</hi> 14.12.2. Men uſually riſe from ſleep refreſhed with it, in a better plight then they were before, ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal when it awakes, ſhall put on immortality;</hi> when I awake up after thy likeneſs, I ſhall be ſatisfied with it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15. Why then theſe blubbered cheeks, this immoderate Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for the death of our friends, ſince they are but aſleep in the Lord, and ſhall be brought with him to glory? <hi>plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere non eſt eorum qui ſpem habent, tu autem qui expectas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectionem, cur luges &amp; lamentaris,</hi> let wretched and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe infidels lament, why doſt thou grieve, that expects a reſurrection, yea, it is the very reaſon why the Apoſtle calls
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119997:11"/>death here but a ſleep in the Lord, becauſe from the hope of the reſurrection we might moderate our Sorrow. I would not have you ignorant brethren, concerning them that are aſleep, that you ſorrow not as men without hope, for the godly deceaſed are not loſt for ever, but left for a time; not gone away from us, but ſent to heaven before, and there ſecure of their own immortality, and ſollicitous of our ſafety, deſire our ſociety. For if that be true, that life without Chriſt is death, then this is as true, that death in Chriſt is life, for bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord: Haſt thou then loſt a Son or a father, a wife or a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? why ſhouldſt thou grieve at their advancement, for they have but changed a croſs for a crown, a vale of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for eternity of happineſſe; who could they now ſpeak with us, they would adviſe us with our Saviour, weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves, I have loſt a Clod of earth, and inheritance of a Span, but I have found an everlaſting Crown of Glory. Mourn indeed we may, ſo ſaith St. <hi>Auguſt. Contriſtemur in noſtrorum mortibus,</hi> we may mourn for the death of our friends, becauſe we have loſt them, but comfort our ſelves, becauſe we ſhall one day enjoy them. Mourn indeed we may for them, but moderately, ſo ſayes the ſon of <hi>Sirach;</hi> thus did <hi>Abraham</hi> for <hi>Sarah,</hi> the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for <hi>Moſes,</hi> and 'twas a cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews, no leſſe venerable then ancient, man go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his long home, and the Mourners walk about the Streets, <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 12.15. 'twas accounted no leſſe then an act of love in our Saviour when <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wept, ſee how he loved him? <hi>Pietas plorare jubet,</hi> for love indeed commands a tear, but faith forbids a deluge. That Counſel which <hi>Seneca</hi> gave his friend <hi>Polybius,</hi> may ſerve for a Chriſtians imitation; reaſon hath done enough if ſhe reſtrain the Exceſſe of Sorrow, but to have it wholy rooted out, no man ought either to hope or deſire it; let our hearts flow, let them be ſtayed, let our ſighs be drawn from the bottome of our hearts, but let them have an end; for though we may enbalme our dead friend with a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119997:12"/>tear; yet we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take heed that we deluge not our faith in the Gulph of deſpair: Sorrow we may ſo far as it is agreeable with the rules of humanity and true piety, but if it exceed the bounds of Chriſtian moderation, we ſhew our ſelves rather hopeleſſe Infidels, then believing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; That advice of the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> is good and remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> 38.16.17. <hi>My Son pour forth tears over the dead and begin to mourn as if thou hadſt ſuffered great harm thy ſelf, and then cover his body according to his appointment, and neglect not his burial; Make a grievous lamentation and be earneſt in mourning, and uſe lamentation as he is worthy, and that a day or two, leaſt thou be evil ſpoken of, and then comfort thy ſelf for thy heavineſs,</hi> and as it is verſe 23. <hi>ſeeing the dead is at reſt, let his remembrance reſt, and comfort thy ſelf again for him, when his Spirit is departed from him;</hi> where he ſhews that there are three things that are due to the dead, Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, mourning, and moderation in mourning; the two former you have and are ſtill performing; 'tis my part, though intereſſed in the loſſe, to moderate the laſt; not to perſwade you to become ſenſeleſſe <hi>Stoicks,</hi> unconcerned in the loſſe of a friend; but true Chriſtians, <hi>Nam non luge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re inhumanum eſt, nimium lugere muliebre; illud rigidi eſt pectoris, iſtud mollis &amp; abjecti,</hi> not to be ſenſible of the loſs of a friend is little leſſe then inhumanity, to grieve a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove meaſure, womaniſh, the one argues a flinty, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a faithleſs heart.</p>
            <p>But perhaps thou wilt ſay I have loſt a dear friend, a moſt loving husband, one in whoſe breaſt dwelt nothing but goodneſſe and piety; ſhall thy paſſion ſtill make thee ſenſeleſſe? wilt thou make that an argument to encreaſe thy grief, which ſhould be the chiefeſt motive to augment thy comfort, for thus dying they are happy, for the death of ſuch are precious in the ſight of God; who therefore takes them out of this miſerable world, that he might take them to himſelf; could you love them and yet greive that they are happy, could they be thus happy and not dye? in truth, nature knows not what ſhe would have, we can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119997:12"/>abide our friends miſerable in their ſtay, nor happy in their departure; True, if they were periſhed or utterly loſt, I could not blame you, if you then took up <hi>Rachels</hi> complaint; but ſince Death is their preferment, ſuch love which moves you ſtill to lament, is injurious. Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> puts this queſtion, why Children and Patents, Wife and Husband, enjoy not one the other ſo long now, as in the dayes of the <hi>Patriarchs?</hi> and gives this reaſon, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Sarahs</hi> behaviour towards <hi>Abraham: Quoniam e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vivente deum praetulit,</hi> becauſe whilſt he lived, ſhe prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God before him. And again, ſpeaking of <hi>Abraham</hi> towards <hi>Sarah, Quoniam câ etiam vivâ deo magis audivit quà ipſam;</hi> becauſe whilſt ſhe lived, he hearkned more, to God then her: Neither for the love of Husband nor of Wife, nor for the care of Childe, did any one provoke God to anger; and concludes, <hi>ne diligas maritum pluſquam deum, &amp; nunquam ſenties viduitatem;</hi> love not thy Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band more then God, and thou ſhalt never feel Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowhood, for thou ſhalt either enjoy him, or God who will be better to thee then ten Husbands; for God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times robs us of thoſe friends which we, nay which God himſelfe loves beſt, and that both for their, and our ſakes: for their ſakes he takes them from the evill to come, for our ſakes weaning us from the love of the World, by depriving us of thoſe Jewells, which did ſeem moſt precious unto us, and therefore let God have them with cheerfulneſſe, and we ſhall one day enjoy God with them in glory. Thus <hi>David</hi> comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf for the death of his Son, I ſhall go to him, but he ſhall not return to me.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Is Death but a Sleep? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> why then ſhould the ſad tole of Mortality diſhearten us? or the approaches of death terrifie us? do men fear to ſleep, eſpecially when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve they ſhall wake again? true, were Life ſo pleaſant, the long ſleep of Death might ſeem ſomewhat dreadfull? doe but ask the Patriarch <hi>Jacob.</hi> and he will rell that life is not onely ſhort but ſoure: <hi>For and evil are the dayes of my
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119997:13"/>Pilgrimage;</hi> here how prettily St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> emblemes it in his tender Infant, <hi>nondum loquitur, &amp; tamen prophetat,</hi> Tears are the firſt Rhetorick that he uſeth, by which, before he can ſpeak he Propheſies, and by a dumb kind of Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wailes out the ſtory of Mans ſorrow here. Well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might the <hi>Graecian</hi> call the firſt day of our life <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the beginning of conflicts, and therefore the <hi>Thracians</hi> did celebrate the day of their Death with Mirth, and the day of their Birth with Mourning; yea, ſaith the wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach,</hi> better is the day of our Death, then the day of our Birth: Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives this reaſon for it, <hi>quia per vitam tranſitus ad mortem,</hi> becauſe by Life we paſſe to Death, and by Death we return unto Life; ſome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore derive the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Death, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe it brings us unto God that made us; for death doth not only free us from miſeries, but conveighs us to happineſs, here we have but <hi>arrham ſpiritus,</hi> the earneſt of the Spirit, there we have <hi>pretium,</hi> the full price; here we dwelt but in Cottages, whoſe foundation is in the Duſt, but Death brings us to an habitation made without hands; now we have converſed with Men, there we ſhall have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Saints, and fellowſhip with the Angels; enjoy <hi>viſionem illam beatificam,</hi> the immediate fruition of God and Chriſt; let them ſpruce <hi>Agags</hi> cry out, <hi>amara mors,</hi> Death is bitter; faint-hearted <hi>Adrians</hi> expoſtulate with their trembling Souls, <hi>Quaenum abibis in loca?</hi> whether art thou going O my doubtful and trembling Soul? whilſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and faithful <hi>Hilarions</hi> cheerfully reſigne their Souls into the hands of him that gave them, with an <hi>egredere ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mea, quid times, egredere, quid dubitas?</hi> get thee gone O my Soul, what doſt fear? get thee gone, what doſt thou doubt? haſt thou ſerved Chriſt almoſt theſe ſeventy years, and now doſt thou fear to dye? Chriſtians ſhould be of that courage, that they ſhould fear nothing but fin; for why ſhould a man fear Death, which doth but reſtore him to him that made him? <hi>time at mortem, qui deum non timet; ſed ſi ſperare deſideras, deſine timere:</hi> Let him fear Death that fears not God, for nothing makes Death ſo terrible, as a bad
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119997:13"/>Life. Let then the fear of God inlarge thy heart, and then thou needſt not fear the day of Death: for here is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, the good Mans hope is ever in Death, but the worldling ends his hope and happineſſe when he dyes: As <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid to <hi>Elias,</hi> ſo ſaith he to Death, <hi>haſt thou found me O mine enemy?</hi> whereas the other ſaith as <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imaaz,</hi> let come and welcome, for he is a good Man and cometh with good things. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> indeed was wont to call Death, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt terrible of all terrible for ſo it is to the Faithleſſe and wicked Man, to whom it is but the beginning of endleſſe torments; but not to the childe of God, to whom it is but a change, a paſſage to a better life: it cannot be terrible unto them, for ſin, the ſting is pulled out, and though it may kiſſe, yet it cannot hurt them, therefore Chriſt bids them, <hi>be of good cheer, for I have overcome death mors morte redempta, O Death, I will be thy Death:</hi> ſo that now to Gods children it is an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. That which was the wages of Sin, is now made the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Righteouſneſſe ſo ſaith <hi>Nazianzen, ita paena ipſa in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſer cordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſit:</hi> Theſe were therefore the comfortable words of a Mother to her dying Son, <hi>peto nate ſuſpice coelum</hi> &amp;c. I prethee my Son look up into Heaven, for thy Life is not taken away, but changed or a better: for ſaith <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus, transfertur vita morte, non aufertur,</hi> Life is but chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, not taken away by Death; when the Sun Sets, he Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth he Sets in our Hemiſphere, and Riſeth in another: ſo the faithful, though he Sets here, yet he Riſeth in Heaven. O then, the more then thrice happy condition of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers who can look Death in the face with a ſmiling coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, whilſt they look through it at Glory: who can behold God as their Father? the offended, their ſurety? the Judge their Saviour? who can therefore reſigne their Soules with that Swan-like <hi>Simeon,</hi> into the hands of their Redeemer? <hi>Now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen thy Salvation.</hi> Conſider this and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thou prophane Atheiſt, whoſe deſtruction draweth nigh, for whom is reſerved the blackneſſe of darkneſſe; ſcoff not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119997:14"/>too faſt, Chriſt ſhall have his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his appearing, <hi>deſuper ac ſuperne,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> above and below; the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his Glory, the brightneſſe of his coming, rendring vengeance to ſuch who know not God, but mock at his coming. Conſider this thou careleſſe and ſecure Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and do no longer dally with thy Repentance, for after Death there is no place left for it; think not to be of the Church Triumphant, unleſſe by Faith thou art a Member of the Militant; think to dye the Death, unleſſe thou doſt ſtrive to live the life of the Righteous, for he that will dye comfortably, muſt live piouſly; a lively Faith in this, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides Salvation, which after is not to be obtained. Death is a ſummoner to Judgement, this Life is the way, whilſt we are in the way let us make our attonement, and defer not ſaith the Son of <hi>Sirach,</hi> til Death, to be juſtified. O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, all you that hear me this day, and neglect no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to have an intereſt in Chriſt by Faith, that when Death ſhall come to ſummon us, it may prove but a ſleep, the Grave a Down Bed, and the Reſurrection a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, at which time we ſhall be caught up in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens to meet the Lord, and ever remain with him in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting bliſſe and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>I have now done with my Text, and come to ſpeak ſomething concerning the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts tell us, that Images are <hi>laicorum libri,</hi> Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Books; I am ſure that dead Bodies are <hi>vivorum libri,</hi> living mens books, wherein every every one may read a true leſſon of his inevitable mortality; <hi>ſero aut citius,</hi> ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or later to the ſame place, for Death is impartial, and ſpares neither Peaſant nor Prince.</p>
            <p>When I look upon your habit and countenances, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but read in them the Emblemes of true grief and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: but when I behold this pious Ceremony, it doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe beſpeaks not onely your Charity, but likewiſe your hope and expectation of a Reſurrection to life, elſe why this Funeral pomp and ſolemnity? indeed Tears and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations are oppoſite to hope, but a ceremonious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119997:14"/>doth both manifeſt and beſpeak it; for if the dead riſe not, why are ye then Baptized for the dead? why do you waſh them? <hi>Calvin</hi> on the 9. of the <hi>Acts</hi> intimates the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>ut in morte ipſa viſibilis aliqua reſurrectionis imago piorum animos in bonam ſpem erigeret,</hi> That in Death it ſelf ſome viſible repreſentation of the Reſurrection might erect the mindes of the faithful unto a good hope, undoubtedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, that that very Body ſhould hereafter appear as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable before the Tribunal of Jeſus Chriſt, as after waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it ſeemed clean and ſpotleſſe before the eyes of men. Tell me ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine, De Civ. Dei,</hi> 1. Why was <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt</hi> regiſtred for burying the Dead? why the Women for anoynting? <hi>Joſeph</hi> for embalming the body of our Saviour? <hi>Non quod ullus cadaveribus ſenſus,</hi> not that the Bodies were ſenſible of this courteſie, but to ſhew that our Bodies though dead, belong unto the Lord, and to confirm our Faith in the Reſurrection: Thus whilſt our Faith adorns a Funeral, a Funeral may encreaſe our Faith. Thoſe diſpoſitions therefore are little below Barbarous, which ſnarle at a decent interment of the dead, for whom not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. I have not ſo much charity to pray, that it may not be their fate to be buried like an Aſſe, having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sepulcher nor Sexton; as it was ſaid of <hi>Jehoiakim,</hi> they ſhall not lament for him ſaying, Ah my Brother, or Ah my Siſter! they ſhall not lament for him, ſaying, Ah Lord, or All his glory! but ſhall be Buried with the Burial of an Aſſe, drawn and caſt forth beyond the gates of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not but it is expected, that I ſhould ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning this our deceaſed brother; but I wiſh there had been choice made of one, whom cuſtome had better vers'd in theſe funeral Panegyricks, and parts enab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to have lim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d forth his worth in a more lively Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, But ſince 'tis my task, give me leave to ſtrow ſome flowers upon his Herſe, and be your remembrancer of his vertues; whoſe name ſhall not rot like the wicked, but like a jewel ſhall remain unto poſterity, for the righteous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119997:15"/>ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance: So that to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea to commend the dead, we have warrant not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the cuſtome of the Greeks, the Romans, but Gods ancient people the Jews, and the Primitive Chriſtians, whoſe funeral Orations are ſtill extant; nay that little good we find in bad men deſerves a regiſter; <hi>David</hi> himſelf pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd <hi>Saul</hi> an <hi>Epicaedium, Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> were lovely and pleaſant in their lives, and in their death they were not divided, ye Daughters of <hi>Iſrael</hi> weep over <hi>Saul,</hi> who cloathed you in Scarlet with other delights, a <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p>To begin therefore from whence he had his beginning, he was deſcended from an antient and Worſhipful Family, which hath been alwaies accounted no ſmall bleſſing, as a ſtrong obligation, and ſpur to Worthy and Noble actions, which were ſuch in him, that his perſonall Vertues, did adde a luſtre to his naturall Honour. After the care of his Parents and Maſter had fitted him for <hi>Oxford,</hi> he ſpent ſome time there under the care and tuition of <hi>Dr. Prideaux.</hi> Thence travailing in the company of Sir <hi>Arthur Hopton,</hi> the Kings Agent, through <hi>France</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> and returned by <hi>Geneva,</hi> having his ſoul untainted either with the pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous ſuperſtition of the one, or the Phanatick no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of the other; neither affecting the ſupercilious gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of <hi>Spaniard,</hi> nor the fantaſtick levity of the <hi>French,</hi> the uſual diſeaſe of travail; but returning with ſo much of either, as might ſerve to make him an accompliſh'd Gentleman &amp; ſerviceable to his Country, had he not lived in an age wherein honeſty and loyalty hath been accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a crime, and a bar to honourable Employments. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards marrying with a virtuous and pious Lady, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from an ancient and worſhipful family in <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> living together all their time in true Love and Amity, having not only their hands in marriage, but as it is ſaid of <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> their ſouls knit together in true af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and though God bleſſed them not with any off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, yet his love was ſuch to her, that he might well
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119997:15"/>have ſaid as <hi>Elkannah</hi> did to to <hi>Hannah,</hi> am not I better to thee then ten Sons, and though he had none of his own, yet ſome Orphans might ſay of him, that they found in him a father, witneſs his care and expence towards his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews and Neeces, whoſe Charity was not only confined to his own relations, but that it overflowed to others; breeding up the child of a neighbour deceaſed miniſter at School, and not leaving him there, but maintaining him at <hi>Oxford,</hi> whoſe neceſſity I doubt not, will ſtill be ſupplyed by his charitable Lady.</p>
            <p>Yea ſuch was his charity in general unto all, not only thoſe of his own and neighbouring pariſhes, but whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe neceſſity doth comprize under that title, that I beleive none ever went away unſatisfied, or not having ample occaſion to bleſſe God for him; ſo that I may ſay of him as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſaid of himſelf; <hi>ne mihi accidat, ut dum pauperes egeant, ego diteſcam &amp; illorum inopiae non ſuccurram;</hi> the neceſſity of whom he charitably ſupplyed, ſo far from oſtentation or phariſaical pride, that I may ſay of him, that his left hand knew not what his right hand did, ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling opportunity to ſupply the neceſſity of thoſe, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had lived in a condition to ſupply the wants of others.</p>
            <p>For his Hoſpitalitie towards all, rich and poor, that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much commends, and <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo loved; yea ſo loveth ſtill ſaith <hi>Chryſologus, Serm.</hi> 121. <hi>ut parum ſe beatum eredidit, &amp;c.</hi> that he would ſcarce think himſelf happy in heaven, if he were deprived of the uſe and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thereof, it was ſuch, that by it together with his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and affability, he won ſo much upon the affections of all, that he became the love and darling of his Country; who doubtleſs would have teſtified it in an ample manner, by their free and voluntary choice of him, to have ſerved as a Member in this ſucceeding Parliament; on which the eyes of moſt (next under God I hope) are fixed for the ſettlement of this diſtracted and almoſt diſtructed nation; had not God thought it fitter, by a writ of remove, to take
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119997:16"/>him from this Lower to that Upper houſe, and to make him a Member of his own heavenly Court.</p>
            <p>For his Piety towards God, he was a conſtant frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Ordinances, making his houſe a little model of a Church, where (beſides his own private Devotions) Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Evening Sacrifices were daily offered unto God, and I doubt not, acceptably, they being preſented unto him in the ſame language and form, which the Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, greatly admiring at the Piety and Prudence of the Church in her choice compoſure, from the which none of his Servants could preſume to be abſent, without a ſevere check, reſolving with <hi>Joſhuah, I and my houſhold will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when his Sickneſſe, which began with a Cold, and continued with a violent Cough, had confined him to his Chamber, and his Friends became more fearfull of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; I began a ſerious diſcourſe with him concerning Death and Mortality, and a due preparation thereunto: he replyed, that if God thought it fitteſt to take him out of this world, he could patiently ſubmit to his Will; but if God would be pleaſed to ſpare him, he ſhould be thankful, and was reſolved by Gods grace to ſpend that time which he ſhould add to his dayes, more to Gods glory; much like that of the Prophet <hi>David, O let my Soul live, and it ſhall praiſe thee;</hi> returning me hearty thanks for my ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al advice and Counſel; telling me withall, that the oftner my diſcourſe was to this purpoſe, the welcomer I ſhould be into his preſence; which encouraged me unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of my duty, with the greater cheerfulneſſe and alacrity; ever finding his diſcourſe ſo full of Piety and true contrition, enough to have confirmed a Chriſtian, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted an Atheiſt.</p>
            <p>But growing weaker in Body, but increaſing in Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſtrength, he deſired to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, which he did with Humility, Devotion and Cheerfulneſſe, ſpending the remainder of his time, which was ſome two dayes and nights, almoſt wholly in Prayer,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119997:16"/>which was performed by my ſelfe and a neighbour-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: he in the interim preaching unto us, ſuch Sermons of Piety and Contrition, expreſſing ſo much grief and ſorrow for his ſins, ſuch a true and and lively Faith in the Mercy of God, for the merits of his Saviour, for the pardon and remiſſion of them, that it were little leſſe then uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe it ſelfe to doubt his Salvation.</p>
            <p>And when his loving and careful Conſort, who would never leave nor forſake him, untill Death writ the Bill of Divorce; lay by him, bemoaning her loſſe, and bathing his Pillow with her Tears: he prayed her to be more cheerfull, and not endeavour to keep Death from him, which would ſoon bring him to Chriſt: the like he ſaid to his Servants ſtanding about his Bed, lamenting their loſſe in him.</p>
            <p>But when his Tongue, which had been an inſtrument to bleſſe and praiſe God, could no longer perform its office, his eyes and hands became his Orators to Heaven for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, with which emploring the aſſiſtance of thoſe that ſtood by in prayer, which being ended, he turned aſide, and not long after fell aſleep, reſigning his Soul into the hands of his Redeemer.</p>
            <p>In fine, he was, I had almoſt ſaid what was he not? he was a good Chriſtian, a loyall Subject, preferring his duty and a good Conſcience, (of the which too many have made Shipwrack) before his F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>are; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Son of the Church, a lover of the Orthodox Clergy, a releiver of the wants of thoſe that ſuffered for the teſtimony of a good Conſcience, a moſt indulgent Husband, a loving Brother, a faſt Friend, a good Landlord, a juſt man, a charitable benefactor to the Poor, loving and liberal to his Servants, and now doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe is entred into his Maſters joy.</p>
            <p>But perhaps thou wilt reply, what, no droſſe among all this gold? yes doubtleſſe, otherwiſe he had been more then Man; he had no queſtion his failings, his ſins and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo had, and ſo have the beſt of Saints, which he did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with humility and ſorrow: what they were, is not my buſineſſe to proclaim, if thou knoweſt any, let me
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119997:17"/>adviſe thee to learn by him to amend them in thy ſelfe; and ſince he had ſo much grace to repent of them, God ſo much mercy to forgive them, do thou have ſo much Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to forget them; burying them in his grave, where we are going to lay his body, that chamber of reſt, untill Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to awake him, and us altogether with him, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bliſſe both of Body and Soul. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119997:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
